<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Articles to be enquired of in the generall visitation of the Archdeacon of the diocesse of Glocester holden in the yeare of our Lord, 1635.</title>
            <author>Church of England. Diocese of Gloucester.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1635</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 32 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00184</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10214.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S4280</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">24048106</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 24048106</idno>
            <idno type="VID">27116</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00184)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 27116)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1815:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Articles to be enquired of in the generall visitation of the Archdeacon of the diocesse of Glocester holden in the yeare of our Lord, 1635.</title>
                  <author>Church of England. Diocese of Gloucester.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[T. Cotes],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1635.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Name of publisher suggested by STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴ (last leaf blank).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Lincoln College Library (University of Oxford).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Government.</term>
               <term>Visitations, Ecclesiastical --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:27116:1"/>
            <p>ARTICLES TO BE ENQVIRED OF In the Generall Viſitation of the <hi>ARCHDEACON</hi> of the Dioceſſe of GLOCESTER.</p>
            <p>Holden in the yeare of our Lord, 1635.</p>
            <figure>
               <head>POST TENEBRAS LVX</head>
            </figure>
            <p>Printed at <hi>London,</hi> 1635.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="directions">
            <pb facs="tcp:27116:2"/>
            <head>Directions to be followed by the Church-wardens and Sidemen for the orderly and legall making of their preſentments.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Et the Church-wardens and Sidemen upon the receipt of the Booke of Articles, addreſſe themſelves to the Miniſter of their Pariſh, or in his abſence, to ſome other Clerke that can reade and write (in caſe they themſelves be ignorant) and let the Clerke write in a faire ſheete of paper the head of the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentment thus, <hi>The Preſentment of the Church-wardens and Sidemen of  <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap>  exhibited in the Viſitation of the Arch Deacon of</hi> Gloceſter <hi>held at  <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap>  the  <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap>  day of  <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap>  Anno Dom.</hi> 1635. Then taking the booke of Articles, and diſtinctly reading the ſame from Article to Article (as by the tenor of their oath they are bound to doe) at the end of every Article let the Clerke en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire what they can ſay to that Article. If they have ought to ſay, then let him write thus, <hi>To the first Article concerning the Church wee preſent that, &amp;c.</hi> And ſo proceeding in the ſeverall enquiries ſet downe in the Booke, let them not faile impartially with due reſpect unto their oath, to anſwere to every Article negatively or affirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively as truth ſhall lead them, and to preſent the ſeverall Offences and Offenders within their Pariſh therein enquired after, ſeriouſly conſidering how dreadfull and damnable a ſinne it is to profane Gods moſt holy Name by perjury and forſwearing themſelves; eſpecially in ſuch a caſe, where they make themſelves acceſſary and liable to thoſe ſinnes and the puniſhments of the ſame, which by their connivence and concealing they ſuffer to paſſe unpuniſhed in others.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="oath">
            <head>The Tenor of the Oath to be miniſtred to the Church-wardens and Sidemen.</head>
            <p>YOu ſhall Sweare, that upon due conſideration of the Articles delivered you in charge, all affection of hatred, favour, hope and feare being lay'd aſide, you ſhall preſent all and every ſuch perſon that now is or of late was within your Pariſh, as hath committed any offence, or made any default men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned or meant in thoſe or any of thoſe Articles, or which is vehemently ſuſpected or defamed for any ſuch offence or default, wherein you ſhall deale faithfully and fully; ſo helpe you God according to the Contents of this Booke.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="articles">
            <pb facs="tcp:27116:2"/>
            <head>ARTICLES</head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning the Church.</head>
               <p n="1">1 <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Mprimis</hi> Whether have you in your ſeverall Churches and Chappells, a faire great Bible of the laſt Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the Bookes of Common Prayer and Homilies, the Booke of Conſtitutions or Cannons Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, and a parchment Regiſter booke, provided for Chriſtnings, Marriages and Burialls, duely and exactly kept accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the conſtitutions in that caſe provided; and a tranſcript thereof brought in yearely within one moneth after Eaſter, in the Lord Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops principall Regiſter his Office?</p>
               <p n="2">2. Item have you a cenvenient ſeate for the Miniſter to reade Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice in, together with a comely Pulpit, ſet up in a convenient place, with a decent Cloth or Cuſhion for the ſame; a comely large ſurpleſſe; A Font of ſtone in the ancient uſuall place; a convenient and decent Communion Table, with a carpet of ſilke, or ſome other decent ſtuff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> layed upon the ſame in time of Divine Service, and a faire linnen cloth thereon at the Communion time; a faire Communion Cup with a cover both of ſilver, with all other things and Ornaments neceſſary for the celebration of Divine Service, and adminiſtration of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments; and a ſtrong cheſt for kéeping of the Ornaments of the Church &amp; Regiſter book, with another cheſt for the almes of the poore, both having thrée lockes and keyes? Have you the ten Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ſet upon the Eaſt end of your Church or Chappell, where the people may beſt ſée and read them, and other ſentences of holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures written on the wals for the ſame purpoſe; A Table of the degrées, wherein by law men are prohibited to marry, ſet up and faſtned in ſome convenient place?</p>
               <p n="3">3. Whether is your Church or Chappell with the Chancles thereof, and your Parſonage or Vicarage houſe, and all other houſing thereto belonging, in good reparations, and decently and comely kept, as
<pb facs="tcp:27116:3"/>
well within as without, the ſeates well maintained, your Church-yards well fenced and kept entire from encroachment and without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe? If not, then through whoſe default?</p>
               <p n="4">4 Are any of your Bells or other Church-goods wanting, any glaſſe windowes defaced, or ancient Monuments of your Church ſpoyled, and by whoſe fault?</p>
               <p n="5">5. Have the Church-wardens there ſuffered any playes, feaſts, banquets, Church-ales, drinkings, or any other profane uſages to be kept in your Church, Chappell, or Church-yard, or bells to be rung either unſeaſonably or ſuperſtitiouſly, contrary to the 88 Cannon?</p>
               <p n="6">6. Is there a true Terriar of all the glebe-land, houſes, Tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Orchards, Gardens, and portions of Tythes (whether within your Pariſh or without) belonging to your Parſonage or Vicarage, delivered into the Office of the Regiſter of this Dioceſſe?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning the Clergie.</head>
               <p>FIrſt, Whether doth your Miniſter diſtinctly and reverently reade Divine Service upon Sundayes, Holydayes and their Eeves, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Wedneſdaies, alſo and Fridaies according to the booke of Common Prayer at fit and uſuall times? And doth he duly obſerve all the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, rites and ceremonies preſcribed in the ſaid Booke of Common Prayer, as well in reading publicke Prayers, and the Letany, as alſo in adminiſtring the Sacraments, ſolemnizing of Matrimony, viſiting the ſicke, burying the dead, Churching of women, and all other like Rites and Offices of the Church, in ſuch manner and forme as by the booke of Common Prayer is enjoyned without any omiſſion or additi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thereunto?</p>
               <p n="2">2 Doth your Miniſter adminiſter the holy Communion ſo often and at ſuch times, as that every Pariſhioner may receive the ſame at the leaſt thrice in every yéere, whereof once at Eaſter? And doth he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the ſame himſelfe on every day that he adminiſtreth ſo others? And doth he deliver the Bread and Wine to every Communicant ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally and knéeling, and uſe the words of inſtitution according to the Booke, at every time that the Bread and Wine is renewed, Can. 21? And is warning given by him before hand for the Communion, Can. 22: as likewiſe for Holydayes and Faſting dayes, Can. 64?</p>
               <p n="3">3. Whether hath your Miniſter admitted to the holy Communion any ſtrangers of another Pariſh, any ſciſmatickes, any which be open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly knowne to live in ſinne without repentance, or have maliciouſly and openly contended with their neighbours before reconcilement, or laſtly
<pb facs="tcp:27116:3"/>
any Church-wardens that in their preſentments have notoriouſly and wilfully forſworne themſelves? Or hath your Miniſter rejected from the Communion any without ſuch juſt caſes?</p>
               <p n="4">4. Hath your Miniſter Curate, or Lecturer publickely or privately affirmed or maintained any thing repugnant, contrary or derogatory to the 39 Articles, Canons of the Church, Bookes of Common Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, Homilies or conſecrating of Biſhops and Prieſts, or the forme of Government by Biſhops and others in this Church of England?</p>
               <p n="5">5. Hath your Pariſh beene any time deſtitute of a Curate? and by whoſe default? And is your Parſon or Vicar continually reſident with you upon his Benefice? or if he be lawfully abſent or reſide upon ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Benefice, doth he ſupply his abſence by a Curate that is a licenſed Preacher for that cure; or if the ſmalneſſe of the Living will not beare a Preaching Curate, doth he Preach himſelfe uſually at both his Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefices, Can. 47?</p>
               <p n="6">6. Whether is your Miniſter a Preacher allowed? if ſo, doth hée Preach every Sunday (having no lawfull impediment) either in his owne cure with you, or ſome other néere adjoyning where no Preacher is? If he be not an allowed Preacher, doth he procure Sermons to be preached amongſt you monethly at leaſt by Preachers lawfully licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, if his Living will beare it: and on every Sunday when there is no Sermon Preached, doth he read ſome one of the Homilies preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed by authority?</p>
               <p n="7">7 Doth your Miniſter or Curate ſerve more Cures than one? If ſo, what are they, and how farre diſtant? And whether being no Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher allowed he take upon him to expound the Scriptures openly?</p>
               <p n="8">8. Hath any perſon béene admitted to Preach within your Church or Chappell, but ſuch as you have well knowne to be ſufficiently licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed? whom have you ſo admitted, and how often have any ſuch béene admitted to preach, and by whoſe procurement? And have you cauſed every ſtrange Preacher, licenſed or not licenſed, to ſubſcribe his name, together with the day when he Preached, Can. 50 and 52? And if he were licenſed, then by whom he was ſo licenſed? And whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther have they or any other preached in your Church, not being ſober<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and decently apparelled, Can. 74. as in a cloake and not in a gowne?</p>
               <p n="9">9. Doth you Miniſter and Lecturer uſe to pray before his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons for the Kings Majeſtie, the Quéene, Prince <hi>Charles</hi> and all the Royall Progeny, giving unto the King ſuch Style and Titles as by law are due unto his Highneſſe, exhorting his Pariſhioners to yéeld him obedience accordingly? And alſo in theſe ſayd Sermons doe they pray
<pb facs="tcp:27116:4"/>
for all Arch-biſhops, Biſhops, and other Eccleſiaſticall perſons, Can. 55?</p>
               <p n="10">10. Doth your Lecturer or Lecturers, reade Divine Service accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Common Prayer Booke in his Surplice and Hood before the Lecture? And doth every Beneficed man, though chiefly attending to Preach, and having a Curate under him for other duties, yet in his owne perſon reade divine Service two ſeverall Sundaies both mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and evening every yeere: And doe both Lecturer and Preacher themſelves adminiſter the Sacraments alſo twice every yeere, obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving all the ceremonies in the booke of Common Prayer eſtabliſhed, Can. 56?</p>
               <p n="11">11. Whether doth your Miniſter at the reading of publicke Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and adminiſtration of the Sacraments weare the Surplice, and a Hood thereon agreeable to his degree in the Vniverſity, if he be a gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duate? Can. 58.</p>
               <p n="12">12. Doth you Miniſter every Sunday and Holyday, before eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Prayer, for halfe an houre or more, examine and inſtruct the youth and ignorant perſons of the Pariſh, in the ten Commandements, the Articles of the Beleefe, the Lords Prayer, and the Sacraments according to the Catechiſme ſet forth in the booke of Common Prayer onely, whereby the children of the Pariſh may be prepared for Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation? Can. 59. And are the afternoones Sermons turned into Catechizing by queſtion and anſwere?</p>
               <p n="13">13 Whether hath your Miniſter without licence from the Arch-bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, the Biſhop of the Dioceſſe or his Chancellor, ſolemnized marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age betwixt any parties in a time prohibited, or the banes not being three ſeverall Sundaies or Holy dayes firſt publiſhed in time of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine ſervice, in the ſeverall Churches or Chappels of their ſeverall abode, Can. 62? or hath he married any not betwixt the houres of eight and twelve in the forenoone, or without a ring, or the parties being of another Dioceſſe, or when the parties are under the age of one and twenty yeeres before ſuch time as the Parents or Guardians have m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>de knowne unto him their conſent thereunto Can. 100?</p>
               <p n="14">14. Whether doth your Miniſter in the Rogation dayes uſe the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ambulation of the circuit of the Pariſh, according to the ancient and laudable cuſtome of the Church: and in the ſame perambulation bleſſe the fru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tes of the earth, and move the people to give thankes to God for his benefits uſing ſuch Pſalmes, Prayers and Homilies, as are to that end ſet forth?</p>
               <p n="15">15. Whether doth any man being not in orders take upon him to
<pb facs="tcp:27116:4"/>
exerciſe any part of the Miniſteriall duty in the Church? and what is his name?</p>
               <p n="16">16. Doth your Miniſter, every ſixe moneths denounce in his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh-Church, all ſuch of his Pariſh, as doe ſtand contumacious under the ſentence of excommunication, not ſéeking to be abſolved? Or hath he admitted any perſon excommunicate into the Church, without a certificate of his abſolution from the Ordinary, or other competent Iudge under his Seale? or hath he ſtayed the publication of any ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communications, or ſuſpenſions?</p>
               <p n="17">17. Doth your Miniſter, being a Preacher, labour diligently from time to time, to conferre with, and thereby to reclaime, the Popiſh Recuſants in his Pariſh, from their errors, if any ſuch be there. Can. 66? And doth he carefully viſite the ſicke, according to Can. 67?</p>
               <p n="18">18. Whether is your Parſon, Vicar, Lecturer, or Curate, too much frequent, or over converſant with, or a Favourer of Recuſants, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he may be ſuſpected not to be ſincere in Religion?</p>
               <p n="19">19. Hath your Miniſter, or any other, taking upon him the place of a Miniſter, Preached, Baptized Children, Solemnized Marriage, Churched any woman, or Miniſtred the holy Communion, in any pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate houſe or houſes, otherwiſe then by Law is allowed? If yea, then where, whom, and how often?</p>
               <p n="20">20. Hath your Miniſter taken upon him to appoint any publicke or private faſts, propheſies, or exerciſes, not approved by law, or publicke Authority? Or hath he attempted under any pretence either of poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or obſeſſion, by faſting and prayer, to caſt out devils, Can. 72? Or hath he uſed to meete with any other perſon or perſons in any private houſe or any other place, there to conſult how to impeach or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eprave the Booke of Common Praier, or the Doctrine, or Diſcipline of the Church of England, Can. 73? If yea, then ye ſhall preſent him, and all that ioyne with him, in any of the premiſſes.</p>
               <p n="21">21. Whether hath your Miniſter refuſed, or delayed to Chriſten any Child that is brought to the Church to him upon Sundaies or Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidayes, or to bury the dead, ſuch as ought to be interred in Chriſtian buriall, having convenient warning before? Eſpecially whether hee hath neglected to baptize any Infant in da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ger, having béene duly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed of his weakeneſſe, ſo that the child hath dyed by his default, without Baptiſme? Or hath he neglected to uſe the ſigne of the Croſſe in Baptiſme; or baptized any in a Baſon, or other veſſell, and not in the ordinary Font; or admitted any Father, to be God-father to his owne child, or ſuch to be God-fathers, or God-mothers, as have not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived
<pb facs="tcp:27116:5"/>
the holy Communion? Or hath he baptized any children that were not borne in the Pariſh, or buryed any in Chriſtian buriall, that dyed excommunicate, or wilfully deſtroyed himſelfe?</p>
               <p n="22">22. Hath your Miniſter, admitted any woman to be Churched, that was begotten with childe in adultery, or fornication, without licence of his Ordinary?</p>
               <p n="23">23. Whether doth your Miniſter uſe ſuch decency, and comlineſſe in his apparell, as by the 74 Can. is enioyned him, as well at home as abroad? And is he of ſober behaviour, and one that doth not uſe ſuch bodily labour as is not ſéemely for his Function and calling?</p>
               <p n="24">24. Is your Miniſter noted, or defamed to have obtained his Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefice, or his Orders by Simonye, or otherwiſe to be Simoniacall, or ſciſmaticall, or reputed to be an incontinent perſon, or doth he kéepe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man or woman in his houſe, that are ſuſpected to be either of evill Religion, or bad life? Or is he a common drunkard, or a common haun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Tavernes, Alehouſes, or other ſuſpected places; a common game<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, or player at dice, or other unlawfull game, a common ſwearer, or one that neglecteth his ſtudy, or is any other way notorious, whereby he is offenſive and ſcandalous to his Function or Miniſtry?</p>
               <p n="25">25. Doe you know in your Pariſh, any that having heretofore taken upon him the Order of Prieſthood, or Deacon, hath ſince relinquiſhed the ſame, living as a Lay man, and neglecting his Vocation?</p>
               <p n="26">26. Whether hath your Miniſter, Curate, and Lecturer, duly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved the Kings Maieſties Inſtructions, and his Declaration for ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of Queſtions in difference, ſet before the Articles of Religion Printed 1629? And hath your Miniſter read the Conſtitutions and Canons Eccleſiaſticall, once every yeare upon ſome Sundayes or Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidaies in the afternoone before divine Service?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning Schoolemaſters.</head>
               <p n="1">1 HOw many Schoolemaſters, or Teachers, of Youth have you in your Pariſh, either publicke or private, and what be their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall names? Whether be they of good and ſincere Religion, life and converſation, and diligent in teaching and bringing up of Youth; Have they béene licenſed for Schoolemaſters, by the Ordinary?</p>
               <p n="2">2. Whether your Schoolemaſters doe come themſelves, and bring their Scholers to the Church, to heare divine Service and Sermons, and ſuch as are of age to receive the Communion? Doe they inſtruct their Scholers in the grounds of the Religion now eſtabliſhed in this Church of England, and no other; or doe they teach them any other
<pb facs="tcp:27116:5"/>
Catechiſme than is authorized by publicke authority, or not examine them therein once every wéeke at the leaſt? And what Catechiſme is it they doe ſo teach?</p>
               <p n="3">3. Whether your Schoolemaſter or Schoolemaſters doe teach his or their Scholers any other Grammer than that which is called the Kings Grammer, ſet forth by the authority of King <hi>Henry</hi> the eighth, teaching the Preſcript forme thereof, whereby the Scholers may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly underſtand their Grammar rules and conſtructions?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Pariſh Clarkes and Sextons.</head>
               <p n="1">1 VVHether have you a fit Pariſh Clarke, aged twenty yeares at leaſt, of honeſt converſation, able to reade and write? And whether he and the Sexton be payd their wages without fraud, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the ancient cuſtome of your Pariſh? if not, then by whom is it ſo defrauded and denied? by whom are they choſen? Is the Clarke approved by the Ordinary, diligent in his Office, and ſerviceable to the Miniſter? And doth he meddle with nothing above his place, as Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of Prayers, Churching of women, burying the dead, or ſuch like?</p>
               <p n="2">2 Doth your Clarke or Sexton kéepe the Church cleane, the doores lock't at fit times? Is any thing loſt or ſpoyled in the Church through his default? Are the Communion Table, Font, Bookes and other Ornaments of the Church kept faire and cleane? Doth he ſuffer any unſeaſonable ringing or any profane exerciſe in your Church or Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell? or doth he (when any is paſſing out of this life) neglect to toll a hell having notice thereof?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning the Pariſhoners.</head>
               <p n="1">1 VVHether is there any within your Pariſh that hath or doth impugne or impeach any way the Kings Maieſties Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy in cauſes Eccleſiaſticall, or the oath of Supremacy or of Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance? or that denieth the Church of <hi>England</hi> by law eſtabliſhed under the Kings moſt excellent Majeſty to be a true &amp; Apoſtolicall Church, teaching and maintaining the doctrine of the Apoſtles? or that impug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth and ſpeaketh againſt the Booke of Common Prayer, any of the Articles of Religion agreed upon in Anno 1562, or the Rites and cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies eſtabliſhed in the Church of <hi>England</hi> or the lawfull uſe of them, or the government of the Church of <hi>England</hi> by Arch-biſhops, Biſhops, Archdeacons and the reſt that beare office in the ſame, affirming the ſame to be Antichriſtian or repugnant to Gods Word; or laſtly that
<pb facs="tcp:27116:6"/>
doth impugne the forme of conſecrating and ordaining of Archbiſhops, Biſhops, Prieſts, and Deacons, affirming that the ſame is repugnant to the Word of God, or that they who are ſo ordered, are not lawfully made?</p>
               <p n="2">2 Is there any in your pariſh that doth hold or frequent any Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles or private congregations, or make or maintaine any private or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders or conſtitutions agreed upon in any ſuch private aſſemblies, other than are in the Cannons ſet forth by publicke authority? Or have you any Schiſmatickes that ſeparate themſelves from the Church of <hi>England,</hi> or any that maintaine Sciſmatickes?</p>
               <p n="3">3. Whether any of your Pariſh have profaned the Lords day com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly called Sunday, or other Holydayes by working or labouring in their manuall trades, by ſelling, or buying, or kéeping open their ſhops for ſale of wares, by lurking and tippling in Tavernes or Alehouſes, eſpecially in the time of Divine Service? And whether any Inne-kéepers, Alehouſe-kéepers, Victualers or others permit any perſon or perſons in their houſes, to eate, drinke or play, in the time of Common Prayer or Sermon, on Sundayes or Holydaies?</p>
               <p n="4">4 Whether any of your Pariſh diſturbe, let or diſcourage others from lawfull ſports and recreations upon the Lords day, ſo farre as they are allowed by the Kings declaration in that behalfe? Or doe any of your Pariſh abuſe that liberty allowed them, by uſing unlawfull ſports, as Beare-bayting, Bull-bayting, Interludes or Bowling upon the Lords day; or by uſing lawfull recreations before the end of all Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Services for that day, or having abſented themſelves from the ſame?</p>
               <p n="5">5 Whether any of your Pariſh being ſixtéene yéeres of age or up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, or others lodging or commonly reſorting to any houſe within your Pariſh, have wilfully abſented themſelves from your Pariſh Church upon Sundayes or Holidayes at Morning or Evening prayers or came late to Church, or departed out of Church before the end of Service and Sermon without ſome great cauſe? Or have any beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved themſelves irreverently during the time of divine Service, cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring their heads, or not knéeling when the generall confeſſion, Let any and other Prayers are read, and ſtanding up at the Beleefe, or not do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing lowly reverence at the name of our Lord Ieſus, or talking, wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king ſléeping or any other way buſying themſelves in the Church then in quiet attendance unto Gods Service? Or have any diſturbed the Miniſter either praying or preaching by word or déede?</p>
               <p n="6">6 Whether any of your Pariſh being ſiixtéene yéeres old and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<pb facs="tcp:27116:6"/>
have not received the holy Communion in your Church thrice this laſt yéere, whereof once at Eaſter, and that knéeling? And who are they?</p>
               <p n="7">7. Is there any in your Pariſh that refuſe to have their children Baptized, or themſelves to receive the Communion at the hands of your Miniſter, for ſome exceptions againſt him? And what excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons doe they alledge? And doe any of or in your Pariſh refuſe to have their children Baptized in your Pariſh Church, according to the forme preſcribed in the booke of Common Prayer?</p>
               <p n="8">8 Whether any of your Pariſhioners being warned thereof, have not ſent their children, ſervants, and apprentices to the Catechiſme upon Sundayes and Holydayes before evening Prayer, to heare, and to be inſtructed therein? you ſhall preſent their names.</p>
               <p n="9">9. How many Inhabitants within your Pariſh men or women, above the age of 16 yéeres doe refuſe to frequent Divine Service eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed by publicke authority of this Realme, or to receive the holy Communion? preſent their names, and of what degrée, ſtate, or trade of life they are.</p>
               <p n="10">10 Doe any of the Inhabitants of your ſayd Pariſh entertaine within their houſe any ſojourners, lodgers, or any common reſorters and gueſts, who refuſe to frequent Divine Service, or receive the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Communion as aforeſayd? What be their names? of what quality or condition are they?</p>
               <p n="11">11. Whether any of the ſaid Popiſh Recuſants, or other Sectaries, are of inſolent behaviour, or doe boldly buſy themſelves, in ſeducing, and withdrawing of others?</p>
               <p n="12">12. How long the ſaid Recuſants, have abſtained either from Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Service, or from the Communion, as aforeſaid: And if any of them have lately reformed themſelves, what be their names?</p>
               <p n="13">13. What perſons within your Pariſh, either for the offence afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, or for any other contumacy or crime, doe remaine excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated? What be their names, and for what cauſe, and how long have they ſtood excommunicated, and what perſon or perſons doe wittingly, and uſually kéepe them company?</p>
               <p n="14">14. Have any in your Pariſh married within the degrées forbidden by law? Where and by whom? Or doth any couple married lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, now live apart, without due ſeparation by the Law: or any here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore divorced, kéepe company with any other at bed or board as man and wife?</p>
               <p n="15">15. Whether have you any in your Pariſh, to your knowledge or by
<pb facs="tcp:27116:7"/>
common fame and report, which have committed adultery, fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or inceſt, or any Bawds, harbourers or receivers of ſuch perſons? Or which are by common ſame, reputed for common drunkards, blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemers of Gods holy name, common ſwearers, filthy ſpeakers, ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, ſlanderers, ſowers of diſcord among their neighbours, or ſpeakers againſt Miniſters, Marriages, Vſurers, contrary to the Statute made in the two and twentieth yeare of our late Soveraine King <hi>Iames.</hi> Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniacall perſons, or periured in any Court Eccleſiaſticall, or any that uſe Inchantments, Sorceries, Charmes, or Witch-crafts (which are not made felony by the Statutes of this Realme) or any that ſeeke to ſuch for helpe? You ſhall not faile to preſent them all.</p>
               <p n="16">16. Have any in your Pariſh, harboured any woman with childe unmarried, conveying, or ſuffering her againe to depart without due pennance? You ſhall truely preſent, as well the party harbouring, as harboured, and who is ſuſpected to hau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e committed the incontinency with her: Or is any, heretofore ſuſpected or detected of incontinency, and therefore departing out of your Pariſh, returned now againe? Or in what place elſe is he or ſhée now abiding to your knowledge, or at you have heard? You ſhall not faile to preſent the whole truth in that behalfe.</p>
               <p n="17">17. Be there any in your Pariſh, that retaine, or ſell, utter, diſperſe, carry, or deliver to others, any Engliſh Bookes, or Writings, either of Papiſts, or Sectaries touching, and againſt the Religion, State, or Government Eccleſiaſticall of this Realme, or kéepe any monuments of ſuperſtition uncancelled, or undefaced?</p>
               <p n="18">18. Whether any of your Pariſhoners, have uſually gone to heare Prayers, or Sermons, in other Churches? Or have they communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated or baptized their children in any other Pariſh, or brought ſtrange Miniſters into their owne houſes, to baptize their children privately, according to their owne fantaſies?</p>
               <p n="19">19. Hath any of your Pariſh, behaved himſelfe irreverently, in word or déed, towards your Miniſter or his Vocation, by quarrelling, ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, ſlanderous ſpéeches, or libels? Or hath any offered violence, or quarrelled with any other in the Church or Churchyard; or uſed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe diſorderly in the Church, by filthy or profane talke, or any other rude or immodeſt behaviour?</p>
               <p n="20">20. Whether hath your Miniſter, or any elſe of your Pariſh, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the privily and conſent of the Ordinary, cauſed any to doe penance, or be puniſhed, either openly or otherwiſe for any crime puniſhable, by Eccleſiaſticall lawes only? And what be the names of the parties, that
<pb facs="tcp:27116:7"/>
have puniſhed, and have béene ſo puniſhed; in what maner, and for what cauſe?</p>
               <p n="21">21. Be there any in your Pariſh, who will come to heare the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, but not to the publicke Prayers, according to the Booke, making a ſciſme, or diviſion as it were betwéene the uſe of publicke Prayer and Preaching?</p>
               <p n="22">22. Doe any Women of your Pariſh, after Child-birth, refuſe to come to the Church, to give God thankes for their ſafe delivery, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Booke of Common Prayer? Or do any neglect to kéepe the faſting daies, appointed by the lawes:</p>
               <p n="23">23. Whether have you knowne or heard of any Fidlers, or Min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrels, or any which goe under the name of Muſitians, within this Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, that either at Weddings, Churchings, or any other Feaſts, or meetings, have ſung or uſe to ſing any ſongs, ballads or rimes, tending to the diſgrace of Religion, or the Miniſters thereof; or tending to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faneneſſe, or the corruption of good manners? You ſhall truely preſent the names of ſuch if you know or can learne them; as alſo the names of the houſholder, or houſholders, where they have ſung ſuch ſongs, as alſo the particular names of them, before whom they have ſung them?</p>
               <p n="24">24 Whether doe the Surveiers of your high wayes looke diligently to the mending of the Church-wayes; that the Pariſhioners may conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently come to Church from all places of the Pariſh in Winter time?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning the Churchwardens and Sidemen.</head>
               <p n="1">1 VVHether doe yée the Churchwardens and Sidemen from time to time take care that no idle perſons or loyterers a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide either in the Churchyard or Church porch in Service or Sermon time but cauſe them either to come into the Church to heare Divine Service, or to depart and not diſturbe ſuch as be hearers there? And doe ye take care that the Pariſhioners duely reſort to the Church every Sunday and Holyday, and there ſo remaine during Divine Service and Sermon? And that none be tippling or drinking in any Ale-houſe, Inne, Taverne, or Victualling houſe of your Pariſh during the times aforeſayd, as farre as you are able to hinder it?</p>
               <p n="2">2 Doe ye aſſiſt your Miniſter diligently in bringing the youth of your Pariſh to Catechizing; in the Perambulation the Rogation dayes, and ſuch other things as ſend to the furtherance and advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Gods Service: eſpecially in taking diligent héede and care that
<pb facs="tcp:27116:8"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or ſomtyme <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>?</p>
               <p n="5">5. Doth any man trouble or moleſt you for doing your duties?</p>
               <p n="6">6. If you know of any other matter of Eccleſiaſticall cognizance, worthy preſentment in your iudgement above not expreſſed, you ſhall likewiſe preſent the ſame by vertue of your oath.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
